Part of learning a programming language is
to learn how to convert data from one type
to another. This conversion knowledge is necessary
because, in many cases, data can either be input
as an incorrect data type or imported as a wrong
data type. Here is an example related to the
code we are building for simple games within
Python. Line 2 of this 121-conversion file
shows a variable that stores a rating someone
enters. That rating is supposed to be a whole
number. I will run this code and enter a floating
decimal number. We see two problems here. First,
the decimal number was accepted. Secondly, this
result does not look like the number times 100,
which is the calculation that is supposed to take
place on line 3. There are three basic programming
concepts I want to cover here in addition to
the data type conversions we are covering in
this topic. First, when troubleshooting,
fix one problem at a time. Sometimes,
fixing one problem either fixes multiple problems
or causes a problem elsewhere. But, if you try to
fix numerous problems at once and the fix does
not work, identifying the other problems the
fix causes can be tough. The second lesson to
learn here is to know, when an input is taken,
what kind of data is stored in the input variable
by default? In our case, the input is a string
because this calculation below displays the
input value 100 times rather than multiplying
it by 100. What does this situation tell us?
That the default data type for an input is a
string. While that works for many apps, this
one needs the rating to become a number. Thus,
we will convert the rating to an integer using the
int function, which I will wrap around the rating
variable on line 3 through placing the cursor in
front of rating, typing int, and then wrapping a
set of parentheses around rating, so that the
rating is converted to an integer just before
the calculation occurs. Thirdly, this course will
teach you a lot about functions and methods. A
function is a procedure that performs an action—in
this case, converting one data type to another.
Python has a variety of built-in functions, such
as int for converting to integers and str for
strings, among others. Additionally, you'll learn
how to define your own custom functions. A method
is a specific type of function that belongs to an
instance of a class or an object and can access or
modify the instance or object to which it belongs.
We will see an example of a method later in the
course. For example, in 113-numbers, we can run
the is_integer() method on the [line 4 variable
that holds the number 2 as a float] variable,
which is an instance of the float data type, to
confirm that it is an integer as well as a float.
This is a built-in method for the float data type.
You can also create methods for your own data
types and classes. I will run the code again,
enter 2.2 again, and we have a good news-bad news
situation. The good news is the previous problem
is gone. However, a new problem is here: we are
told we cannot concatenate, meaning combine a
string with an integer. Some languages implicitly
convert data types to avoid this problem. Python
is not one of them. Thus, we need to convert this
result on line 4 to a string, because we are now
trying to concatenate a string, an integer,
and another string, which is not allowed.